<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml"
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
 <!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "release-notes.ent" >
 %myents;
]>
<article xml:lang="en" xml:id="rnotes"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>&rnotes;</title>
 <info>
  <releaseinfo>&rversion;</releaseinfo>
  <productname>&thisflavor;</productname>
  <productnumber>&version;</productnumber>
  <date><?dbtimestamp format="Y-m-d"?></date>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    &thisflavor; is a free and Linux-based operating system for your PC, Laptop
    or Server. You can surf the Web, manage your e-mails and photos, do office
    work, play videos or music and have a lot of fun!
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker>
    <dm:url>https://bugzilla.opensuse.org/enter_bug.cgi</dm:url>
    <dm:product>openSUSE Distribution</dm:product>
    <dm:component>Release Notes</dm:component>
    <dm:assignee>sknorr@suse.com</dm:assignee>
   </dm:bugtracker>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>

 <para condition="beta">
  This is the initial version of the release notes for the forthcoming
  &thisversion;.
 </para>
 <para condition="maintained">
  The release notes are under constant development.
  To find out about the latest updates, see the online version at
  <link xlink:href="https://doc.opensuse.org/release-notes"/>.
  The English release notes are updated whenever need arises. Translated
  language versions can temporarily be incomplete.
 </para>
 <para condition="unmaintained">
  The end of the maintenance period for &thisversion; is now reached. To keep
  your systems up-to-date and secure, upgrade to a current &opensuse; version.
  Before starting the upgrade, make sure that all maintenance updates for
  &thisversion; are applied.
 </para>
 <para condition="unmaintained">
  For more information about upgrading to a current &opensuse; version, see
  <link xlink:href="http://en.opensuse.org/SDB:Distribution-Upgrade"/>.
 </para>
 <!-- Previous Release Notes -->
 <para>
  If you upgrade from an older version to this &thisflavor; release, see
  previous release notes listed here:
  <link xlink:href="http://en.opensuse.org/openSUSE:Release_Notes"/>.
 </para>
 <para>
  <phrase condition="beta">This public beta test is part of the &opensuse;
  project.</phrase> Information about the project is available at
  <link xlink:href="https://www.opensuse.org"/>.
 </para>
 <para condition="beta;pre">
  Report all bugs you encounter using this prerelease of &thisflavor; &version;
  in the &opensuse; Bugzilla. For more information, see
  <link xlink:href="http://en.opensuse.org/Submitting_Bug_Reports"/>. If you
  would like to see anything added to the release notes, file a bug
  report against the component <quote>Release Notes</quote>.
 </para>
 <para condition="maintained">
  To report bugs against this release, use the &opensuse; Bugzilla. For more
  information, see
  <link xlink:href="http://en.opensuse.org/Submitting_Bug_Reports"/>.
 </para>

 <sect1 xml:id="installation">
  <title>Installation</title>

  <para>
   This section contains installation-related notes. For detailed upgrade
   instructions, see the documentation at
   <link xlink:href="https://doc.opensuse.org/documentation/leap/startup/html/book.opensuse.startup/part.basics.html"/>.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.install.minimalinstall">
  <!-- https://bugzilla.suse.com/show_bug.cgi?id=947712 -->
  <!-- https://bugzilla.opensuse.org/show_bug.cgi?id=951866 -->
   <title>Minimal System Installation</title>
   <!-- FIXME: Is this still accurate, patterns and all or is this affected
   by decisions made on the SLE side? -->
   <para>
    To avoid some big recommended packages from being installed, the pattern
    for minimal installations uses another pattern that creates conflicts with
    undesired packages. This pattern,
    <literal>patterns-openSUSE-minimal_base-conflicts</literal>, can be removed
    after installation.
   </para>
   <para>
    Note that the minimal installation has no firewall by default. If you need
    one, install <literal>firewalld</literal>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.install.uefi">
   <title>UEFI&mdash;Unified Extensible Firmware Interface</title>
   <para>
    Prior to installing &opensuse; on a system that boots using UEFI (Unified
    Extensible Firmware Interface), you are urgently advised to check for any
    firmware updates the hardware vendor recommends and, if available, to
    install such an update. A pre-installation of Windows 8 or later is a
    strong indication that your system boots using UEFI.
   </para>
   <para>
    <emphasis>Background:</emphasis> Some UEFI firmware has bugs that cause it
    to break if too much data gets written to the UEFI storage area. However,
    there is no clear data of how much is <quote>too much</quote>.
   </para>
   <para>
    &opensuse; minimizes the risk by not writing more than the bare minimum
    required to boot the OS. The minimum means telling the UEFI firmware about
    the location of the &opensuse; boot loader. Upstream Linux kernel features
    that use the UEFI storage area for storing boot and crash information
    (<literal>pstore</literal>) have been disabled by default. Nevertheless, it
    is recommended to install any firmware updates the hardware vendor
    recommends.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.install.uefi-part">
  <!-- bnc#850056 -->
   <title>UEFI, GPT, and MS-DOS Partitions</title>
   <para>
    Together with the EFI/UEFI specification, a new style of partitioning
    arrived: GPT (GUID Partition Table). This new schema uses globally unique
    identifiers (128-bit values displayed in 32 hexadecimal digits) to identify
    devices and partition types.
   </para>
   <para>
    Additionally, the UEFI specification also allows legacy MBR (MS-DOS)
    partitions. The Linux boot loaders (ELILO or GRUB 2) try to automatically
    generate a GUID for those legacy partitions, and write them to the
    firmware. Such a GUID can change frequently, causing a rewrite in the
    firmware. A rewrite consists of two different operations: Removing the old
    entry and creating a new entry that replaces the first one.
   </para>
   <para>
    Modern firmware has a garbage collector that collects deleted entries and
    frees the memory reserved for old entries. A problem arises when faulty
    firmware does not collect and free those entries. This can result in a
    non-bootable system.
   </para>
   <para>
    To work around this problem, convert the legacy MBR partition to GPT.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <!-- text via boo#1045124, underlying issue: boo#1044816 -->
  <sect2 xml:id="sec.install.nouveau-extra">
   <title>Installing the Nvidia Driver Manually</title>
   <para>
    On &thisversion;, you need to uninstall the package
    <package>drm-kmp-default</package> first, before you can manually install
    Nvidia drivers using the <filename>.run</filename> shell script archive:
   </para>
   <screen>zypper rm drm-kmp-default</screen>
   <para>
    If you install the RPMs provided by Nvidia, you will not be affected by
    this issue, because in that case, the package
    <package>drm-kmp-default</package> is replaced during the driver
    installation automatically.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you decide to uninstall Nvidia's driver later,
    make sure to reinstall the package <package>drm-kmp-default</package>.
   </para>
   <para>
    For more information, see
    <link xlink:href="https://bugzilla.suse.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1044816"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.install.hidpi">
   <!-- boo#1090240 -->
   <title>Scaling the Installer UI on Computers with High-DPI Displays</title>
   <para>
    The YaST installer does not scale its UI for High-DPI displays by default.
    If you have a computer with a high-DPI display, you can set YaST to scale
    its UI automatically for the display. To do so, add the parameter
    <literal>QT_AUTO_SCREEN_SCALE_FACTOR=1</literal> to the bootloader
    command line.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="upgrade">
  <title>System Upgrade</title>

  <para>
   This section lists notes related to upgrading the system. For detailed
   upgrade instructions, see the documentation at
   <link xlink:href="https://doc.opensuse.org/documentation/leap/startup/html/book.opensuse.startup/cha.update.osuse.html"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   Additionally, check <xref linkend="sec.package"/>.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.upgrade.423">
   <title>Upgrading from &opensuseleap; 42.3</title>
   <para/>
  </sect2>

 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec.package">
  <title>Packaging Changes</title>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.package.deprecated">
   <title>Deprecated Packages</title>
   <para>
    Deprecated packages are still shipped as part of the distribution but are
    scheduled to be removed the next version of &thisflavor;. These packages
    exist to aid migration, but their use is discouraged and they may not
    receive updates.
   </para>

   <!-- <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <package>example</package>: Replaced by
      <package>example2</package>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist> -->

   <para>
    To check whether installed packages are no longer maintained: Make sure
    that <package>lifecycle-data-openSUSE</package> is installed, then use
    the command:
   </para>
   <screen>zypper lifecycle</screen>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.package.removed">
   <title>Removed Packages</title>
   <para>
    Deprecated packages are not shipped as part of the distribution anymore.
   </para>

   <!-- <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <package>example</package>: Replaced by
      <package>example2</package>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist> -->
  </sect2>

 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="general">
  <title>Desktop</title>

  <para>
   This section lists desktop issues and changes in &thisversion;.
  </para>

  <!--  boo#1059438, boo#1062550 -->
  <sect2 xml:id="sec.general.compose-key">
   <title>No Default Compose Key Combination</title>
   <para>
    In previous versions of &os;, the compose key combination
    allowed typing characters that were not part of the regular keyboard layout.
    For example, to produce <quote>å</quote>, you could press and release
    <keycombo><keycap function="shift"/><keycap>Right Ctrl</keycap></keycombo>
    and then press <keycap>a</keycap> twice.
   </para>
   <para>
    In &thisversion;, there is no longer a predefined compose key combination
    because
    <keycombo><keycap function="shift"/><keycap>Right Ctrl</keycap></keycombo>
    does not work as expected anymore.
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To define a system-wide custom compose key combination, use the file
      <filename>/etc/X11/Xmodmap</filename> and look for the following lines:
     </para>
<screen>[...]
!! Third example: Change right Control key to Compose key.
!! To do Compose Character, press this key and afterwards two
!! characters (e.g. `a' and `^' to get 342).
!remove  Control  = Control_R
!keysym Control_R = Multi_key
!add     Control  = Control_R
[...]</screen>
     <para>
      To uncomment the example code, remove the
      <literal>!</literal> characters at the beginning of lines. However,
      note that the setup from <filename>Xmodmap</filename> will be
      overwritten if you are using <command>setxkbmap</command>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To define a user-specific compose key combination, use your desktop's
      keyboard configuration tool or the command-line tool
      <command>setxkbmap</command>:
     </para>
     <screen>
setxkbmap <replaceable>[...]</replaceable> -option compose:<replaceable>COMPOSE_KEY</replaceable>
     </screen>
     <para>
      For the variable <replaceable>COMPOSE_KEY</replaceable>, use your
      preferred character, for example
      <literal>ralt</literal>, <literal>lwin</literal>,
      <literal>rwin</literal>, <literal>menu</literal>,
      <literal>rctl</literal>, or <literal>caps</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Alternatively, use an IBus input method that allows typing the
      characters you need without a Compose key.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.general.gdm">
   <title>No Screen Lock When Using GNOME Shell But Not GDM</title>
   <para>
    When using GNOME Shell together with a login manager other than GDM, such
    as SDDM or LightDM, the screen will not blank or lock. Additionally,
    switching users without logging out is not possible.
   </para>
   <para>
    To be able to lock the screen from GNOME Shell, enable GDM as your login
    manager:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Make sure that the package <package>gdm</package> is installed.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Open &yast; and from it, open
      <menuchoice><guimenu>/etc/sysconfig Manager</guimenu></menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Navigate to <menuchoice><guimenu>Desktop</guimenu><guimenu>Display
      manager</guimenu> <guimenu>DISPLAYMANAGER</guimenu></menuchoice>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      In the text box, specify <literal>gdm</literal>. To save, click
      <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Reboot.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.desktop.yast-hidpi">
   <!-- boo#1083873 -->
   <title>Scaling the SDDM UI on Computers with High-DPI Displays</title>
   <para>
    The default login manager for KDE, SDDM, does not scale its UI for High-DPI
    displays by default.
    If you have a computer with a high-DPI display, you can set SDDM to scale
    its UI automatically for the display using the configuration file
    <filename>/etc/sddm.conf</filename>:
   </para>
<screen>
[XDisplay]
ServerArguments=-dpi <replaceable>DPI_SETTING</replaceable>
EnableHiDPI=true
</screen>
   <para>
    Replace <replaceable>DPI_SETTING</replaceable> with an appropriate DPI
    value, such as <literal>192</literal>. For best scaling results, use a
    DPI value that is a multiple of the default 96 DPI.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.desktop.yast-hidpi">
   <!-- bsc#1090240 -->
   <title>Scaling the YaST UI on Computers with High-DPI Displays</title>
   <para>
    YaST does not scale its UI for High-DPI displays by default.
    If you have a computer with a high-DPI display, you can set YaST to scale
    its UI automatically for the display. To do so, set the environment
    variable <literal>QT_AUTO_SCREEN_SCALE_FACTOR=1</literal>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.general.mp3-media">
    <title>Playing MP3 Media Files</title>
    <para>
      The codecs to play MP3 media files
      are shipped as part of the standard repository.
    </para>
    <para>
      To use this decoder in gstreamer-based applications and frameworks,
      such as Rhythmbox or Totem, install the package
      <literal>gstreamer-plugins-ugly</literal>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.general.libreoffice.type1">
   <title>No Support for Type-1 Fonts in LibreOffice</title>
   <para>
    LibreOffice 5.3 and higher do not support legacy Type-1 fonts (file extensions
    <filename>.afm</filename> and <filename>.pfb</filename>) anymore. Most
    users should not be affected by this, as current fonts are available
    either in the format TrueType (<filename>.ttf</filename>) or OpenType
    (<filename>.otf</filename>) formats.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you are affected by this, convert Type-1 fonts to a supported format,
    such as TrueType and then use the converted fonts. Conversion is possible
    with the application FontForge (package <package>fontforge</package>) which
    is included in &opensuse;. For information on scripting such conversions,
    see
    <link xlink:href="https://fontforge.github.io/en-US/documentation/scripting/"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.desktop.freetype-rendering-38">
   <!-- boo#1085372 -->
   <title>FreeType Font Rendering Changes</title>
   <para>
    FreeType 2.6.4 has a new default glyph hinting interpreter (version 38)
    that more closely matches other operating systems but may look
    <quote>more fuzzy</quote> to some. To restore the previous FreeType
    behavior, set the following environment variable at any level
    (system-wide, user-specific, or program-specific) of your choice:
   </para>
   <screen>FREETYPE_PROPERTIES="truetype:interpreter-version=35"</screen>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.general.psgml">
   <!-- boo#1080086 -->
   <title>Loading the Emacs <literal>psgml</literal> Module</title>
   <para>
    Because of conflicts with Emacs modules from the default installation,
    &thisversion; can no longer load the
    <literal>psgml</literal> module automatically. For more information, see
    the file <filename>README</filename> from the package
    <package>psgml</package>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <!-- <sect2 xml:id="sec.general.nonoss">
    <title>Non-Oss Repository</title>
    <para>
     After the installation, the non-oss repository is disabled.
    </para>
    <para>
     Enable the <literal>openSUSE-Leap-42.3-Non-Oss</literal> repository using
     YaST or on the command line using zypper:
     <screen>zypper mr -e repo-non-oss</screen>
    </para>
   </sect2> -->
 </sect1>

 <sect1>
  <title>Security</title>

  <para>
   This section lists changes to security features in &thisversion;.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec.general.apparmor-restart">
   <!-- boo#1074097 -->
   <title><command>systemctl stop apparmor</command> Does Not Work</title>
   <para>
    In the past, there could be confusion over the difference between how the
    very similarly named <command>systemctl</command> subcommands
    <literal>reload</literal> and <literal>restart</literal> worked for
    AppArmor:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <command>systemctl reload apparmor</command> properly reloaded all
      AppArmor profiles. (It was and continues to be the recommended way of
      reloading AppArmor profiles.)
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <command>systemctl restart apparmor</command> meant that
      AppArmor would stop, thereby unloading all AppArmor profiles and then
      restart which left all existing processes unconfined. Only newly
      started processes would then be confined again.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    Unfortunately, <systemitem>systemd</systemitem> does
    not provide a solution within its unit file format for the issue posed
    by the <literal>restart</literal> scenario.
   </para>
   <para>
    Starting with AppArmor 2.12, the command
    <command>systemctl stop apparmor</command> will not work.
    As a consequence, <command>systemctl restart apparmor</command> will now
    correctly reload AppArmor profiles.
   </para>
   <para>
    To unload all AppArmor profiles, use the new command
    <command>aa-teardown</command> instead which matches the previous
    behavior of <command>systemctl stop apparmor</command>.
   </para>
   <para>
    For more information, see
    <link xlink:href="https://bugzilla.opensuse.org/show_bug.cgi?id=996520"/>
    and
    <link xlink:href="https://bugzilla.opensuse.org/show_bug.cgi?id=853019"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <!-- <sect1 xml:id="technical">
  <title>Technical</title>
  <para/>

 </sect1> -->
 <!-- <sect1 xml:id="misc">
  <title>Miscellaneous</title>
  <para/>
 </sect1> -->

 <sect1 xml:id="feedback">
  <title>More Information and Feedback</title>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Read the <filename>README</filename> documents on the medium.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     View a detailed changelog information about a particular package from its
     RPM:
    </para>
    <screen>rpm --changelog -qp <replaceable>FILENAME</replaceable>.rpm</screen>
    <para>
     Replace <replaceable>FILENAME</replaceable> with the name of the RPM.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Check the <filename>ChangeLog</filename> file in the top level of the
     medium for a chronological log of all changes made to the updated packages.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Find more information in the <filename>docu</filename> directory on the
     medium.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     For additional or updated documentation, see
     <link xlink:href="https://doc.opensuse.org/"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     For the latest product news, from &opensuse;, visit
     <link xlink:href="https://www.opensuse.org"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   Copyright © <?dbtimestamp format="Y" ?> SUSE LLC
  </para>

 </sect1>
</article>
